 <unitList
      id="siUnits"
      namespace="http://www.xml-cml.org/units/siUnits"
      title="si units dictionary"
      siNamespace="http://www.xml-cml.org/units/siUnits"
      xmlns="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema"
      xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema ../../schema.xsd"
      xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
      xmlns:h="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
      xmlns:dc="http://www.xml-cml.org/dict/dcDict"
      xmlns:siUnits="http://www.xml-cml.org/units/siUnits"
      xmlns:unitType="http://www.xml-cml.org/units/unitTypes"
    >

   <!-- The SEVEN BASE UNITS - (id in brackets)
    
    kilogram - mass (kg)
    second   - time  (s)
    metre    - length  (m)
    ampere   - electrical current (ampere)
    kelvin   - temperature (k)
    mole     - amount of substance (mol)
    candela  - luminous intensity (candela)
    
    All other units can be derived in terms of these.
    -->
    <unit
    title="second"
    id="s"
    symbol="s"
    parentSI="siUnits:s"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:time">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
	<definition>
		The SI base unit of time, equal to the duration of 9192631770 periods of the radiation corresponding 
		to the transition between the two hyperfine levels of the ground state of the 
		caesium-133 atom.
	</definition>
    <description>
	 The second has had many definitions throughout history; originally, it was one sixtieth
	 of one twenty-fourth of a solar day (the factor of sixty coming from Babylonian counting
	 and the factor of 24 from Ancient Egypt).
	 
	 The present definition dates from the Thirteenth General Conference on Weights and Measures,
	 which took place in 1967.
	</description>

    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="metre"
    id="m"
    symbol="m"
    parentSI="siUnits:m"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:length">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<definition>
		The SI base unit of length, defined as the length of the path travelled by 
		light in absolute vacuum during 1/299792458 of a second.
	</definition>	
    <description>
    	The modern metre dates from 1791, when it was defined one ten-millionth of
    	the length of the earth's meridian along a quadrant; it became France's
    	official unit of length in 1793. Until 1960, the metre (like the kilogram)
    	was defined by a prototype - in this case, a platinum-iridium bar; in 1960,
    	the SI defined the metre as 1650763.73 wavelengths of the orange-red 
    	emission line (the 2p10 - 5d5 transition) in the EM spectrum of Krypton-86 
    	in vacuum. Since 1983, the present definition has been used.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="ampere"
    id="ampere"
    symbol="A"
    parentSI="siUnits:ampere"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:current">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <definition>
    	The SI unit of current, defined as that constant current which if maintained
    	in two straight parallel conductors of infinite length and negligible 
    	circular cross-section, placed 1 metre apart in vacuum, would produce between
    	those conductors a force of 2E-7 newton per metre length.
    </definition>
    <description>
	This is equivalent to setting the permeability of vacuum to pi*4E-7 Hm^-1. Prior
	to 1948, the International Ampere (equal to 0.99985 A) was used; it was defined
	in terms of the electrolytic deposition rate of silver.
    </description>
    </unit>    

    <unit
    title="kilogram"
    id="kg"
    symbol="kg"
    parentSI="siUnits:kg"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:mass">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <definition>
	 The SI base unit of mass, defined as being equal to the mass of the international 
	 prototype of the kilogram.
	</definition>
    <description>
	 	It is the only SI base unit that employs a prefix, and the only SI unit that 
 		is still defined in relation to an artifact (a platinum-iridium mass)
		rather than to a fundamental physical property.	
	</description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="kelvin"
    id="k"
    symbol="K"
    parentSI="siUnits:k"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:temperature">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <definition>
    	The SI unit of temperature, defined as 1/273.16 of the thermodynamic temperature
    	of the triple point of water.
    </definition>
    <description>
    	A temperature in Kelvin is measured with respect to absolute zero - where,
    	except for zero-point motion, molecular motion stops. The unit is named after
    	William Thomson, first Baron Kelvin, a Scottish physicist and engineer.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="mole"
    id="mol"
    symbol="mol"
    parentSI="siUnits:mol"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:amount">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
	<definition>
		The SI unit identifying the number of particles in a given amount of matter,
		a dimensionless number equal to the number of elementary entities in 0.012 
		kilograms of carbon 12 where the carbon 12 atoms are unbound, at rest, and 
		in their ground state.
	</definition>    
    <description>
		The number of atoms in 12 grams of carbon 12 is commonly known as Avogadro's
		number; it is approximately 6.0221415E23. Prior to 1959, IUPAP and IUPAC defined
		the mole in terms of oxygen (though the definitions were slightly different
		from each other); in 1959/1960, the two organizations unified on the
		present definition.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="candela"
    id="candela"
    symbol="cd"
    parentSI="siUnits:candela"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:luminous_intensity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
	<definition>
		The SI base unit of luminous intensity, defined as a radiant intensity
		of 1/683 watt per steradian in a given direction from a monochromatic source 
		at 540E12 Hz.
	</definition>
	<description>
    	This is based on an older unit, the candlepower, which was referenced to 
    	the luminous intensity of a "standard candle" of known composition. The
    	frequency chosen is in the visible spectrum near green, which is within
    	the range where the human eye is most sensitive.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <!-- CONVENTIONAL DERIVED UNITS 
    
    These are part of the SI but are not *base* units. -->
    
    <!-- Dimensionless derived units:
    
    radian
    steradian
    
    -->
    
    <unit 
    id="radian" 
    name="radian" 
    parentSI="siUnits:radian"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    symbol="rad" 
    unitType="unitType:angle">
	<metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
	<h:td>m m<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
	<definition>
		The SI unit of plane angle, equal to the angle subtended at the centre
		of a circle by an arc of circumference equal in length to the circle's
		radius.
	</definition>
	<description>
		The radian is therefore formally dimensionless, as it is a ratio 
		of two lengths. There are 2*pi radians in a complete circle.
	</description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="steradian"
    id="steradian"
    parentSI="siUnits:steradian"
    multiplierToSI="1.0"
    symbol="sr"
    unitType="unitType:solid_angle">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
	<h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup> m<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
	<definition>
		The SI unit of solid angle, defined as the solid angle subtended at the 
		centre of a sphere of radius r by a portion of the surface of the sphere
		having an area r^2.
	</definition>
	<description>
		Since the surface area of a sphere is 4*pi*r^2, a sphere measures 4*pi
		steradians. The steradian is the solid analogue of the radian, and like
		that unit, is formally dimensionless (in this case, being the ratio
		of two areas.)
	</description>
	</unit>
	
	<!-- named derived units -->
	
    <unit
    title="Hertz"
    id="hertz"
    symbol="Hz"
    parentSI="siUnits:hertz"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:frequency">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <h:td>s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    		The SI derived unit of frequency, defined as one cycle per second.
    	</definition>
    <description>
	    Periodically varying angles are typically not expressed in Hz, but instead in
	    an appropriate angular unit (such as radians per second).
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Newton"
    id="newton"
    symbol="N"
    parentSI="siUnits:newton"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:force">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>m.kg.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <h:td>m.kg.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    	The SI derived unit of force, defined as the force necessary to accelerate
    	a mass of one kilogram at a rate of 1m s^-2.
    </definition>
    <description>
		Named after Sir Isaac Newton, the Newton was adopted as the name for the MKS
		(direct predecessor of the SI) unit of force in 1948. A small apple, fittingly,
		exerts a gravitational force of about 1N on Earth.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Joule"
    id="joule"
    symbol="J"
    parentSI="siUnits:joule"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:energy">
	<metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>N m</h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.kg.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    	The SI derived unit of energy, defined as the energy required to exert a force of
    	one newton for a distance of one metre.
    </definition>
    <description>
    	This is dimensionally, but not semantically, equivalent to the newton metre, 
    	which is typically used as a unit of torque. It is also, significantly, 
    	the work required to move an electric charge of one coulomb through an electric 
    	potential difference of one volt.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Watt"
    id="watt"
    symbol="W"
    parentSI="siUnits:watt"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:power">
	<metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />    
	<h:td>J/s</h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.kg.s<h:sup>-3</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    		The SI derived unit of power, defined as one joule of energy per second.
 	</definition>
    <description>
		The watt dates back to the Second Congress of the British Association of the
		Advancement of Science in 1889, and is named after James Watt, one of the key
		engineers to the development of the steam engine.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Pascal"
    id="pascal"
    symbol="Pa"
    parentSI="siUnits:pascal"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:pressure">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>N/m<h:sup>2</h:sup></h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.kg.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    	The SI derived unit of pressure, equal to one newton per square metre.
   	</definition>
    <description>
		The pascal, named after Blaise Pascal, is also used to measure stress,
		Young's modulus, and tensile strength. For atmospheric pressures,
		however, it is commonly regarded as an inconveniently small unit.
    </description>
    </unit>
    

	<!-- Electrostatic units
	
	all unitTypes prefixed electric_ -->
	
    <unit
    title="Coulomb"
    id="coulomb"
    symbol="C"
    parentSI="siUnits:coulomb"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:electric_charge">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
	<h:td>s.A</h:td>
	<definition>
		The SI unit of electric charge, defined as the amount of electric charge carried
		by a current of one ampere flowing for one second.
	</definition>
    <description>
		Also the unit of electric flux.
		
		The Coulomb could, in principle, be defined in terms of the elementary charge
		of the electron and the Josephson and von Klitzing constants; in this case,
		the kilogram would become a derived rather than fundamental unit.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Volt"
    id="volt"
    symbol="V"
    parentSI="siUnits:volt"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:electric_potential_difference">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>W/A = J/C</h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.kg.s<h:sup>-3</h:sup>.A<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    	The SI unit of electric potential difference, defined as the potential
    	difference across a conductor when a current of one ampere dissipates
    	one watt of power.
    </definition>
    <description>
		The number of volts is a measure of the strength of an electrical source 
		in the sense of how much power is produced for a given current level. It 
		is named in honor of Alessandro Volta (1745–1827), who invented the voltaic 
		pile, the first chemical battery.
		
		Since 1990 the volt is maintained internationally for practical 
		measurement using the Josephson effect.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Ohm"
    id="ohm"
    symbol="[Omega]"
    parentSI="siUnits:ohm"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:electric_resistance">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>V/A</h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.kg.s<h:sup>-3</h:sup>.A<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    	The SI unit of electrical impedance/resistance; a resistance of one ohm
    	produces a potential difference of one volt when one ampere of current
    	flows through it.
    </definition>
    <description>
		Named after Georg Ohm, the German physicist who discovered Ohm's Law; since
		1990, the unit has been internationally maintained using the Quantum Hall
		Effect and a conventional value for the von Klitzing constant.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Farad"
    id="farad"
    symbol="F"
    parentSI="siUnits:farad"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:electric_capacitance">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>C/V</h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.kg<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.s<h:sup>4</h:sup>.A<h:sup>2</h:sup></h:td>
	<definition>
		The SI derived unit of capacitance, equal to one coulomb of stored charge causing
		a potential difference of one volt across the terminals of the capacitor being
		measured.
	</definition>
    <description>
    	Capacitance is a measure of the total amount of electric charge stored for
    	a given electric potential.
    	
		The farad is a very large unit; typical capacitors are in the microfarad to
		picofarad range. Although the farad is named after Michael Faraday, it should
		not be confused with the Faraday - an older unit of capacitance.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Siemens"
    id="siemens"
    symbol="S"
    parentSI="siUnits:siemens"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:electric_conductance">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>[Omega]<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.kg<h:sup>-1</h:sup> s<h:sup>3</h:sup>.A<h:sup>2</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    	The SI derived unit of electrical conductance, defined as the reciprocal of
    	the system's electrical resistance.
    </definition>
    <description>
		This is equivalent to the obsolete "mho" unit (derived from spelling "ohm" 
		backwards and written with an upside-down capital omega).
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <!-- magnetic units
    
    all unitTypes prefixed magnetic_ -->
    
    <unit
    title="Weber"
    id="weber"
    symbol="Wb"
    parentSI="siUnits:weber"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:magnetic_flux">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />	
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.kg.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.A<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.kg.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.A<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    	The SI derived unit of magnetic flux; a change in flux of one weber per second
    	through a loop will induce an electromotive force of one volt.
    </definition>
    <description>
		The weber, like the farad, is a very large unit.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Tesla"
    id="tesla"
    symbol="T"
    parentSI="siUnits:tesla"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:magnetic_flux_density">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>V.s.m<h:sup>-2</h:sup> = Wb/m<h:sup>2</h:sup></h:td>
    <h:td>kg.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.A<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    	The SI derived unit of magnetic flux density, defined as one weber per
    	metre squared.
    </definition>
    <description>
    	The tesla is the value of the total magnetic flux (in some sense, the "power"
    	of a magnet) over area; hence reducing the affected area generally increases
    	the magnetic flux density.
    	
    	Like many of the other electromagnetic units, one tesla is very large.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Henry"
    id="henry"
    symbol="H"
    parentSI="siUnits:henry"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:magnetic_inductance">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
	<metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>V.s.A<h:sup>-1</h:sup> = Wb/A</h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.kg.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.A<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    	The SI derived unit of magnetic inductance; a circuit with an inductance
    	of one henry gives rise to an EMF of one volt when the rate of change of
    	current in the circuit is 1 A.s^-1.
    </definition>
    <description>
    	Inductance is a measure of how much magnetic flux is produced for a given
    	circuit. 
    </description>
    </unit>

    <!-- Radioactivity -->
    
    <unit
    title="Becquerel"
    id="becquerel"
    symbol="Bq"
    parentSI="siUnits:becquerel"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:radioactivity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <h:td>s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    The SI derived unit of radioactivity, defined as the activity of a quantity of 
    radioactive material in which one nucleus decays per second.
    </definition>
    <description>
 	This, therefore, has the same dimensionality as the hertz (s^-1, reciprocal time)
 	- a frequency, in other words. The reason for having a specific unit for radioactivity is
 	slightly unusual; it was specifically introduced because of the dangers to 
 	human health which might arise from mistakes involving the units reciprocal second. 
 	Using the becquerel unit, a more active (and so, all the other things fixed, more 
 	dangerous) source has a higher number. Using 1/s or s as a second instead may 
 	lead to confusion.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    
    <unit
    title="Gray"
    id="gray"
    symbol="Gy"
    parentSI="siUnits:gray"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:radioactive_absorbed_dose">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <h:td>J/kg</h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
    The SI derived unit of absorbed radioactive dose, defined
    as the absorption of one joule of radiation energy by one kilogram of matter.
    </definition>
    <description>
	Note that these are the same units as the sievert. To avoid any risk of confusion 
	between the absorbed dose and the equivalent dose, one must use the corresponding 
	special units, namely the gray instead of the joule per kilogram for absorbed dose 
	and the sievert instead of the joule per kilogram for the dose equivalent.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Sievert"
    id="sievert"
    symbol="Sv"
    parentSI="siUnits:sievert"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:radioactive_equivalent_dose">
    <metadata name="dc:creator" content="Andrew Walkingshaw" />
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>J/kg</h:td>
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <definition>
	The SI derived unit of equivalent radioactive dose, equal to the absorbed dose
	in grays multiplied by two dimensionless constants - Q, dependent on radiation
	type, and N dependent on all other factors.
    </definition>
    <description>
    The sievert attempts to reflect the biological effects of radiation as opposed to 
    the physical aspects, which are characterised by the absorbed dose, measured 
    in grays.
    
	Note that these are the same units as the sievert. To avoid any risk of confusion 
	between the absorbed dose and the equivalent dose, one must use the corresponding 
	special units, namely the gray instead of the joule per kilogram for absorbed dose 
	and the sievert instead of the joule per kilogram for the dose equivalent.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <!-- chemical properties -->
    
    <unit
    title="Katal"
    id="katal"
    symbol="kat"
    parentSI="siUnits:katal"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:catalytic_activity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>mol/s</h:td>
    <h:td>s<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.mol</h:td>
    <definition>
    The derived SI unit for expressing quantity values of catalytic activity, in
    mol s^-1.
    </definition>
    <description>
    The katal is not used to express the rate of a reaction; that is expressed in moles 
    per second. Rather, it is used to express catalytic activity which is a property of 
    the catalyst. The katal is invariant of the measurement procedure, but the numerical 
    quantity value is not and depends on the experimental conditions. Therefore, in 
    order to define the quantity of a catalyst, the rate of conversion of a defined 
    chemical reaction has to be specified, preferably of the first order, under 
    strictly controlled conditions.

    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <!-- Nameless erived units -->
    
    <unit
    title="Molarity"
    id="molarity"
    symbol="_i_M__i_"
    parentSI="siUnits:molarity"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:molarity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>mol/L</h:td>
    <h:td>10<h:sup>3</h:sup>.m<h:sup>-3</h:sup>.mol</h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Molality"
    id="molality"
    symbol="_i_m__i_"
    parentSI="siUnits:molality"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:molality">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>mol/kg</h:td>
    <h:td>kg<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.mol</h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Square metre"
    id="m2"
    symbol="m2"
    parentSI="siUnits:m2"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:area">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Cubic metre"
    id="m3"
    symbol="m3"
    parentSI="siUnits:m3"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:volume">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>3</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Metre per second"
    id="m.s-1"
    symbol="m.s-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:m.s-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:velocity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m.s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="Metre per second squared"
    id="m.s-2"
    symbol="m.s-2"
    parentSI="siUnits:m.s-2"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:acceleration">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="radian per second"
    id="rad.s-1"
    symbol="rad.s-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:rad.s-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:angular_velocity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="newton second"
    id="n.s"
    symbol="N.s"
    parentSI="siUnits:n.s"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:momentum">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m.s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="newton metre second"
    id="n.m.s"
    symbol="N.m.s"
    parentSI="siUnits:n.m.s"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:angular_momentum">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="newton metre"
    id="n.m"
    symbol="N.m"
    parentSI="siUnits:n.m"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:torque">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="reciprocal metre"
    id="m-1"
    symbol="m-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:m-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:wavenumber">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    id="kg.m-3"
    title="Kilogram per cubic metre"
    symbol="kg.m-3"
    parentSI="siUnits:kg.m-3"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:mass_density">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m<h:sup>-3</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="cubic metre per kilogram"
    id="kg-1.m3"
    symbol="kg-1.m3"
    parentSI="siUnits:kg-1.m3"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:specific_volume">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.m<h:sup>3</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="mole per cubic metre"
    id="m-3.mol"
    symbol="m-3.mol"
    parentSI="siUnits:m-3.mol"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:amount_concentration">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>-3</h:sup>.mol</h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="cubic metre per mole"
    id="m3.mol-1"
    symbol="m3.mol-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:m3.mol-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:molar_volume">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>3</h:sup>.mol<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="joule per kelvin"
    id="j.k-1"
    symbol="J.K-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:j.k-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:heat_capacity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.K<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="joule per kelvin mole"
    id="j.k-1.mol-1"
    symbol="J.K-1.mol-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:j.k-1.mol-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:molar_heat_capacity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.K<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.mol<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="joule per kilogram kelvin"
    id="j.k-1.kg-1"
    symbol="J.K-1.kg-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:j.k-1.kg-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:specific_heat_capacity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.K<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="joule per mole"
    id="j.mol-1"
    symbol="J.mol-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:j.mol-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:molar_energy">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.mol<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="joule per kilogram"
    id="j.kg-1"
    symbol="J.kg-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:j.kg-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:specific_energy">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="joule per cubic metre"
    id="j.m-3"
    symbol="J.m-3"
    parentSI="siUnits:j.m-3"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:energy_density">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="newton per metre"
    id="n.m-1"
    symbol="N.m-1 = J.m-2"
    parentSI="siUnits:n.m-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:surface_tension">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="watt per square metre"
    id="w.m-2"
    symbol="W.m-2"
    parentSI="siUnits:w.m-2"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:heat_flux_density">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.s<h:sup>-3</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="watt per metre kelvin"
    id="w.m-1.k-1"
    symbol="W.m-1.K-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:w.m-1.k-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:thermal_conductivity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m.s<h:sup>-3</h:sup>.K<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="square metre per second"
    id="m2.s-1"
    symbol="m2.s-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:m2.s-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:kinematic_viscosity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    id="pa.s"
    title="Pascal second"
    symbol="Pa.s = N.s.m-2"
    parentSI="siUnits:pa.s"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:dynamic_viscosity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="coulomb per cubic metre"
    id="c.m-3"
    symbol="C.m-3"
    parentSI="siUnits:c.m-3"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:electric_charge_density">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>-3</h:sup>.s.A</h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="ampere per square metre"
    id="a.m-2"
    symbol="A.m-2"
    parentSI="siUnits:a.m-2"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:electric_current_density">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>A.m<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="siemens per metre"
    id="s.m-1"
    symbol="S.m-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:s.m-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:electrical_conductivity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.m<h:sup>-3</h:sup>.s<h:sup>3</h:sup>.A<h:sup>2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="siemens square metre per mole"
    id="s.m2.mol-1"
    symbol="S.m2.mol-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:s.m2.mol-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:molar_conductivity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.s<h:sup>3</h:sup>.mol<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.A<h:sup>2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="farad per metre"
    id="f.m-1"
    symbol="F.m-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:f.m-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:permittivity">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.m<h:sup>-3</h:sup>.s<h:sup>4</h:sup>.A<h:sup>2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="henry per metre"
    id="h.m-1"
    symbol="H.m-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:h.m-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:permeability">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m.s<h:sup>-2</h:sup>.A<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="volt per metre"
    id="v.m-1"
    symbol="V.m-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:v.m-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:electric_field_strength">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg.m.s<h:sup>-3</h:sup>.A<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="ampere per metre"
    id="a.m-1"
    symbol="A.m-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:a.m-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:magnetic_field_strength">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>A.m<h:sup>-1</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="candela per square metre"
    id="cd.m-2"
    symbol="cd.m-2"
    parentSI="siUnits:cd.m-2"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:luminance">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>cd.m<h:sup>-2</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="coulomb per kilogram"
    id="c.kg-1"
    symbol="C.kg-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:c.kg-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:exposure">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>kg<h:sup>-1</h:sup>.s.A</h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>
    
    <unit
    title="gray per second"
    id="gy.s-1"
    symbol="Gy.s-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:gy.s-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:absorbed_dose_rate">
    <metadata name="dc:source" content="Wikipedia" />
    <h:td>m<h:sup>2</h:sup>.s<h:sup>-3</h:sup></h:td>
    <description>
    not yet added
    </description>
    </unit>

 <!-- locally derived units -->    
    <unit
    title="joule per metre"
    id="j.m-1"
    symbol="J.m-1"
    parentSI="siUnits:j.m-1"
    multiplierToSI="1.0" 
    unitType="unitType:energy_length_gradient">
    <metadata name="dc:author" content="petermr, adw, ojd" />
    <definition>
    Gradient of energy with respect to length.
    </definition>
    <description>
    Although formally identical to force, many authors report energy gradients as
    energy per unit length and this unitType preserves the dimensional representation.
    </description>
    </unit>
    
</unitList>
